Edward Grant papers, 1950-2001 C184
Indiana University Archives
Edward Grant papers
1950-2001
Indiana University Archives
Grant, Edward, 1926-2020
C184
24.6 cubic feet
Edward Grant, a Distinguished Professor Emeritus of History and History and Philosophy of Science taught at Indiana University for over thirty years. This collection consists of 24.6 cubic of Edward Grant's papers. Consists of correspondence, research, drafts, publications, and course and lecture notes. By far the largest series in the collection is the Teaching series and includes materials from Grant's years teaching as a graduate student at the Univ. of Wisconsin and then later at Indiana. The bulk of the series, though, consists of folders relating to the courses he taught in the IU Dept. of History and Philosophy of Science. The Publications series contains information on many of Grant's publications, including his books Much ado about nothing and Source book in medieval science.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers. These files are marked RESTRICTED in the finding aid.
Advance notice is required.
Biographical Note
Edward Grant, Distinguished Professor Emeritus of History and History and Philosophy of Science at Indiana University, was born in 1926. He began his higher education at the City College in New York, graduating Cum Laude in 1951, and continued to the University of Wisconsin, where he received his Masters and Doctorate in the History of Science and Medieval History in 1957. During this time, Dr. Grant spent a year at the University of Utrecht as a Fulbright Scholar (1955-1956).
Dr. Grant began his successful teaching career while a graduate student at the University of Wisconsin. He was an assistant to a well-known scholar in the field, Dr. Marshall Clagett, whom he would continue to respect and correspond with throughout his career. Before arriving in Bloomington, Indiana as an Assistant Professor of History, Dr. Grant spent two years teaching at the University of Maine (1957-1958) and Harvard University (1958-1959).
Dr. Grant's teaching career at Indiana University spanned over thirty years, beginning in 1959. He was instrumental in starting the department later to be known as History and Philosophy of Science and became Distinguished Professor of both that department and History. Dr. Grant also served as Chairperson of History and Philosophy of Science between 1973-1979 and 1987-1990.
A distinguished medievalist, Dr. Edward Grant wrote prolifically throughout his professorship at Indiana University. Among his numerous books are the multi-volume A Source Book in Medieval Science and Much Ado About Nothing: Theories of Space and Vacuum from the Middle Ages to the Scientific Revolution. Dr. Grant also published a variety of articles and reviews in such respected journals and publications as Isis, History of Science, Dictionary of Scientific Biography, and The New Catholic Encyclopedia.
In addition to his abundant writings, Dr. Grant was also a prominent member of several organizations, such as the Medieval Academy of America, the Academie Internationale d'Histoire des Sciences, and the History of Science Society for which he served as Vice-President (1983-1984) and President (1985-1986). Dr. Grant was also a frequent lecturer for organizations such as the Phi Beta Kappa Associates Panel of Distinguished Speakers (1990-1998).
Some of Dr. Grant's various achievements are recorded in listings such as Who's Who in America, Directory of American Scholars, Men of Achievement, and Dictionary of International Biography. Dr. Grant died on June 21, 2020.
Arrangement
Organized in six series - Correspondence, Teaching, Student work, Research, Publications and Professional activities.
Scope and Content Note
The Edward Grant papers are organized in six series-- Correspondence, Teaching, Student work, Research, Publications, and Professional activities.
The Correspondence series is arranged alphabetically with the most frequent correspondents making up their own folders. The contents of the letters include insight into Dr. Grant's publications, research, and letters from colleagues and students. Some folders are restricted because they contain detailed research proposals. The Correspondence series comprises 2 cubic feet.
The second series, Teaching, is further organized into two subseries--Dr. Grant's materials before beginning his career at Indiana University and after. The bulk of the series consists of folders relating to a variety of courses taught in the History and Philosophy of Science department at I.U. The folders are arranged by course and consist of exams, questionnaires, readings, and handwritten notes. This series comprises 7 cubic feet.
Dr. Grant's work as a student makes up the third series and consists of notes taken from his undergraduate and graduate courses. Some folders contain original research leading up to his dissertation, of which two copies are included. This series comprises 2 cubic feet.
One of the largest series, Research, is further organized into eight subseries- -Research proposals, Research for articles, Miscellaneous research, and Research for five of Grant's books: (Nicole Oresme: "De Proportionibus Proportionum" and "Ad Pauca Respicientes", Nicole Oresme and the Kinematics of Circular Motion. Tractatus de Commensurabilitate Vel Incommensurabilitate Motuum Celi, A Source Book in Medieval Science, Much Ado About Nothing, and Jordanus de Nemore's Arithmetica (unpublished). Included in this series are several National Endowment for the Humanities and National Science Foundation research proposals, microfilmed manuscripts used for his books, handwritten notes, and Xeroxes. There are five oversized folders that pertain to this series, stored in box 23 of the collection. A box of index notes containing notes from Dr. Grant's extensive research completes the series. This series comprises approximately 4 cubic feet.
The Publications series consists of three subseries--Articles, Reviews, and Materials relating to books. The articles subseries contains drafts, correspondence and some published articles. It is arranged in chronological order and there is one oversized folder stored in the last box. Similarly, the Reviews subseries is arranged chronologically and contains drafts and published reviews. The Books subseries is arranged chronologically and contains galley sheets for some of the books, published copies (not of all books), reviews, and permissions. This series comprises approximately 4.5 cubic feet.
The final series of the collection documents Dr. Grant's Professional activities. It is further organized into five subseries--Professional associations, Professional committees, Lectures, Biographical information, and Office files. The first two subseries consist of correspondence pertaining to various associations and the Committees subseries also includes appraisals of History of Science departments at a number of universities. The Lectures subseries consists of drafts of talks given at conferences, meetings, banquets, and universities. Information about Dr. Grant's various Who's Who Listings and some miscellaneous items are contained in the Biographical subseries, including honors and awards, and memorabilia from Dr. Grant's trip to England. The last subseries is comprised of Dr. Grant's files pertaining to the Department of the History and Philosophy of Science and the Department of History Included are minutes of meetings, faculty annual reports, and book acquisition information. This series comprises approximately 4.5 cubic feet.
Separated Material
Departmental files were removed to create a separate collection (C198).
Related Material
See Collection C198, Indiana University Department of History and Philosophy of Science - Chair's records, 1973-1991
Acquisition Information
Accession 98/028, 98/038, 2000/067, 2001/057
Gift; Edward Grant 1998-2001.
Departmental chairmen (Universities) --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Departmental chairmen (Universities) --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; History teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; History teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Science teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Science teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Source book in medieval science.; Much ado about nothing.; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University -- Faculty -- Correspondence; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Archives; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Correspondence; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Source book in medieval science; Grant, Edward, 1926-2020 -- Much ado about nothing: theories of space and vacuum from the Middle Ages to the scientific revolution; Indiana University. Department of History and Logic of Science -- History -- Sources; Indiana University. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- History -- Sources; Indiana University. Department of History and Philosophy of Science -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; University of Wisconsin -- students -- Archives
- Correspondence, 1957-1996
  - A, 1958; 1980-1996 (Box 1)
  - Ashworth, William, 19 Nov 1984; 25 Nov 1985 (Box 1)
  - Asua, Miguel de, Mar-Jun 1992 (Box 1)
  - B, 1958-1959; 1965; 1973; 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  - Basalla, George, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Brackenridge, Bruce, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Burrows, Barry, undated (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Burton, Dan (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Byrnes, Robert F., 1958-1959; 20 Feb 1985 (Box 1)
  - C, 1978-1988; 1992-1996 (Box 1)
  - Cadden, Joan (Box 1)
    - 1967-1988, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1967-1981 (Box 1)
    - cont., 1967-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1995 (Box 1)
  - Cagle, William, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Capshew, James H., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Caroti, Stefano, 11 Feb 1985; 1995 (Box 1)
  - Chien-Yeh, Yang, 13 Apr 1988; 12 May 1988 (Box 1)
  - Christiansen, Eric H., 1977 (Box 1)
  - Cimino, Guido, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Clagett, Marshall, 1957-1958; 1960-1961; 1977-1987 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, I. Bernard, 1981-1984; 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Cook, Robert, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Crowe, Michael, 1980 (Box 1)
  - D, 1959; 1977-1991 (Box 1)
  - Dales, Richard C., 1978; 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Edward B (Ted), 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - Day, Carol (Box 1)
    - 1975-1986 (Box 1)
    - cont., 1975-1986; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Diamont, Alfred, Aug 1984 (Box 1)
  - Dick, Steven J., 1975-1987 (Box 1)
  - Dougherty, Jude P., 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Drake, Stillman, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - E, 1978-1990 (Box 1)
  - Eastwood, Bruce, 1971; 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - Evensen, Karen, 4 Feb 1991 (Box 1)
  - F, 1959; 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Franz, Frank, Feb 1980 (Box 1)
  - Freudenthal, Gad, 12 Sep 1983; 25 May 1983 (Box 1)
  - G, 1957-1958; 1975; 1980-1996 (Box 1)
  - Gabriel, Astrik L. (Box 1)
    - 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
  - Goddu, Andre, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Grandy, David, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Grant Family cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Gros Louis, Kenneth, 1979; 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Grunbaum, Adolf, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Guerlac, Henry, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - H, 1958; 1968-1998 (Box 1)
  - Hansen, Bert, 18 Sep 1971; 1978-1984 (Box 1)
  - Harris, Steven James, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Harvard University, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Hoskin, Michael, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - I, J, 1975; 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Jennings, Ted, 1978 (Box 1)
  - K, 1976-1990 (Box 1)
  - Korn, Phil, 1986 (Box 1)
  - L, 1976-1986; 1995 (Box 1)
  - Lindberg, David C. (Box 1)
    - 1979-1987 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Livesey, Steven, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Lohr, Charles, 1979-1988 (Box 1)
  - Lowengrub, Morton, 1978; 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Lu, Yan, 18 Apr 1993 (Box 1)
  - M, 1968; 1976-1996 (Box 1)
  - Maienschein, Jane, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
  - McMullen, Emerson Thomas (Box 1)
    - 1988-1991, 1996 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Meyer, Eric, 1984-1991 (Box 1)
  - Meyer, Leslie (Box 1)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Mitchell, Linda, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Multhauf, Robert P., 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Murdoch, John (Box 1)
    - 1961, 1978-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1994 (Box 1)
  - N, 1980-1990 (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation, 1959 (Box 2)
  - North, John D., 1984-1990; 1995 (Box 2)
  - O, 1952-1959; 1964; 1978-1991 (Box 2)
  - Osler, Margaret J. (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - undated (Box 2)
  - P, Q, 1982-1996 (Box 2)
  - R, 1966; 1977; 1982-1996 (Box 2)
  - Rosen, Edward, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Ryan, John W., 1980-1987 (Box 2)
  - S, 1977-1995 (Box 2)
  - Schmitt, Charles B., 1979-1986 (Box 2)
  - Scott, Walter G., 1979 (Box 2)
  - Shaw, James R., 1977-1978; 1986 (Box 2)
  - Shixiong, Sun, 1987-1990 (Box 2)
  - Simmons, George C., 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Joel, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Mark, 1977-1979; 1983; 1992 (Box 2)
  - Sobol, Peter G. (Box 2)
    - 1982-1994 (Box 2)
    - undated (Box 2)
  - Sokal, Michael M, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Solt, Leo F., 1959; 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Souffrin, Pierre, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
  - Swerdlow, Noel, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Sylla, Edith, 1980; 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - T, 1978-1990 (Box 2)
  - Taylor, Kenneth L., 30 Apr 1982; 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - U, V, 1957; 1969; 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - Unguru, Sabetai, 1978-1991 (Box 2)
  - UCLA, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - University of Maine, undated (Box 2)
  - Van Egmond, Warren (Box 2)
    - 1977-1987 (Box 2)
    - undated (Box 2)
  - W, 1957; 1979-1993 (Box 2)
  - Weinstein, Donald, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Wells, Herman B, 1959; 1984; 1990 (Box 2)
  - Wheeler, Helen, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Woolf, Harry, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Y, Z, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
  - Yokoyama, Masahiko, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1977-1991 (Box 2)
  - Letters for Colleagues (Box 2)
    - 1967-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Letters and Proposal Reviews (Box 2)
    - 1981-1986, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Letters for Students, 1973-1993; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Grant's comments on proposals, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Unsolicited Manuscripts, 1983-1999 (Box 2)
- Teaching, 1951-2000
  - Materials prior to Indiana University, 1951-1959
    - University of Wisconsin, History of Science (Box 3)
      - 1a (Clagett), Spring 1951 (Box 3)
      - 1a, quiz materials, Spring 1951 (Box 3)
      - 1b (Clagett), Spring 1954 (Box 3)
      - 1b (Stauffer), Spring 1954 (Box 3)
    - University of Maine (Box 3)
      - History Dept., outlines, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
      - Dept. of History and Gov't., 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - Economic History of Europe, Fall 1957-1958; (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - History of Science, Fall 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - Economic History of Europe, Spring 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - Survey of W. European Civ., Spring 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - History of Science, Spring 1957-1958; (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - History Exams, 1957-1958 (Box 3)
    - Harvard University (Box 3)
      - Natural Sciences 3, 1958-1959; (6 folders) (Box 3)
      - History of Science Tutorial, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
      - History of Science, Lectures, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Old Examinations, 1952-1960 (Box 3)
  - Subseries: Materials relating to courses at Indiana University, 1961- 2000
    - X207--The Occult in Western Civilization (Box 4)
      - Experimental Course Proposal, Fall 1973 (Box 4)
      - Clippings on occult (Box 4)
        - 1974-1994, (3 folders) (Box 4)
        - 1974-1998 (Box 4)
        - 1992-1994 (Box 4)
      - Course Syllabi (Box 4)
        - Fall 1976, 1979; 1980 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1980, 1984; 1985 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1985 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1986 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1987 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1991 (Box 4)
        - Fall 1998 (Box 4)
        - Spring 1998 (Box 4)
      - Questionnaires, Spring 1977-1978 (Box 4)
      - Quiz 2, undated (Box 4)
      - 5 week exams, 1975-1991 (Box 4)
      - 10 week exams, 1976-1988 (Box 4)
      - 15 week exams, 1974-1988 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, outlines, notes, undated; (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Readings Packet, Spring 1998; (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - Introductory Lecture, Fall 1976-1991 (Box 4)
      - Occult Powers, Fall 1979 (Box 4)
      - Magic, Fall 1980 (Box 4)
      - Magic Lecture II, Fall 1991 (Box 4)
      - Magic Lectures, Spring 1998 (Box 4)
      - X207, cont. Astrology, undated (Box 4)
      - Bibliographies on occult topics, undated (Box 4)
      - Egyptian Magic, undated (Box 4)
      - ESP, undated (Box 4)
      - Gnosticism, Cabala, Hermeticism, undated (Box 4)
      - Magic in Middle Ages, undated (Box 4)
      - Medieval Cosmos, undated (Box 4)
      - Notes on evidence, undated (Box 4)
      - Notes on the occult, undated (Box 4)
      - Notes on scientism, undated (Box 4)
      - Notes on skepticism, undated (Box 4)
      - Possession and exorcism, undated (Box 4)
      - Spiritualism, undated (Box 5)
      - Superstition, undated (Box 5)
      - UFOs, undated (Box 5)
      - Witchcraft, undated; (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - Memorabilia from course, undated (Box 5)
    - X211, Survey of the History of Science, Fall 1973 (Box 5)
    - X307 (Box 5)
      - Questionnaire, Spring 1974 (Box 5)
      - Jan 1975 (Box 5)
      - Apr 1975 (Box 5)
    - X336, Religion and Science (Box 5)
      - Handwritten Notes (no order), undated; (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Religion and Science, Fall 1971 (Box 5)
      - Introduction, Fall 1985; (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Egypt and Mesopotamia, Fall 1985 (Box 5)
      - Plato lecture, Fall 1985 (Box 5)
      - Spring 1992 (Box 5)
      - (706) Student papers, Spring 1992 (Box 5)
      - Aristotle lecture, undated (Box 5)
      - Galileo lecture, undated (Box 5)
      - Newton lecture, undated (Box 5)
      - Various lectures, undated; (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - 17th Century England, undated (Box 5)
      - 18th Cent. Theology, undated (Box 5)
      - 19th Cent., undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous papers, undated (Box 5)
      - X336, cont. The advent of Christianity, undated (Box 6)
      - Aristotelianism in 16th Cent., undated (Box 6)
      - Copernicus, undated (Box 6)
      - Eternity of world, undated (Box 6)
      - Genealogy and age of Earth, undated (Box 6)
      - Greek religion, undated; (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Hermeticism, undated (Box 6)
      - Hexaemeral literature, undated (Box 6)
      - Hooykaas, undated (Box 6)
      - Islam, undated; (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Medieval science and theology, undated (Box 6)
      - History of science film course: (Box 6)
        - The Ascent of Man, undated (Box 6)
        - Film Lists, undated (Box 6)
    - M500 Bibliography of medieval studies, undated; Spring 1987; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - X501, History of Science (Box 6)
      - Mimeographed sheets, 1961-1963 (Box 6)
      - Fall 1962 (Box 6)
      - Student Papers, Fall 1962 (Box 6)
    - X502, Medieval Medicine, Spring 1959-1960 (Box 6)
    - X505, History of Science (Box 6)
      - General, Fall 1966-Spring 1991 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous handouts, undated (Box 6)
      - X505/405, Lectures 1-37, 1971; 1979 (Box 6)
      - Introduction, 1977; 1991 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous student papers (Box 6)
        - 1974-1977 (Box 6)
        - 1981, 1985; 1991 (Box 6)
      - Exams (Box 6)
        - 1987, 1989; 1991 (Box 6)
        - Spring 1987 (Box 6)
      - Presocratics (Box 6)
        - Spring 1987 (Box 6)
        - Spring 1989 (Box 6)
        - Spring 1991 (Box 6)
      - Handouts/Exams, Spring 1991 (Box 6)
      - Alchemy, undated (Box 6)
      - X505, cont. Ancient Egypt, undated (Box 7)
      - Ancient and Medieval science, undated (Box 7)
      - Aristotle, undated; (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Aristotle's scientific method, undated (Box 7)
      - Bibliography on the history of medieval science, undated (Box 7)
      - Bibliography on special topics, undated (Box 7)
      - Biographical sheets, undated (Box 7)
      - Early Middles Ages chartres, undated (Box 7)
      - Egypt and Mesopotamia, undated (Box 7)
      - Greek Astronomy, undated (Box 7)
      - Greek Biology, undated (Box 7)
      - Greek Mathematics, undated; (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Greek Medicine, undated (Box 7)
      - Hexaemeral literature, undated (Box 7)
      - Intention and remission of forms, undated (Box 7)
      - Islam, undated (Box 7)
      - Medieval cosmos, undated (Box 7)
      - Medieval dynamics, undated (Box 7)
      - Medieval Latin medicine, undated (Box 7)
      - Medieval optics, undated (Box 7)
      - Mesopotamia, undated (Box 7)
      - X505, cont. Plato, undated (Box 8)
      - Plurality of worlds, undated (Box 8)
      - Presocratics (Box 8)
        - pluralists, atomists, undated (Box 8)
        - monists, undated (Box 8)
      - The problem of motion in middle ages, undated (Box 8)
      - Proportions of motion, undated (Box 8)
      - Science in late antiquity, undated (Box 8)
      - What is motion?, undated (Box 8)
    - X506 (Box 8)
      - Lectures, undated (Box 8)
      - History of Science Survey, Fall 1993 (Box 8)
      - Student papers (Box 8)
        - Fall 1993 (Box 8)
        - Fall 1994 (Box 8)
      - Aristotle celestial region, undated (Box 8)
      - Christianity, undated (Box 8)
      - Latin encyclopedists, undated (Box 8)
      - Neoplatonism, undated (Box 8)
      - Ptolemy, undated (Box 8)
    - X520, Logic of Science, Fall 1960 (Box 8)
    - X521, Student papers, Fall 1968 (Box 8)
    - H610, Philosophy and Science in Medieval Thought (Box 8)
      - Fall 1968 (Box 8)
      - Handwritten notes, Fall 1970 (Box 8)
      - The medieval university, Fall 1981 (Box 8)
      - Medieval intellectual history (Box 8)
        - 1983-1984, (2 folders) (Box 8)
        - Fall 1984 (Box 8)
      - Medieval universities, Spring 1986 (Box 8)
      - Intellectual history and universities, Spring 1987 (Box 8)
      - Fall 1989, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Spring 1992, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - X614, X615, Handwritten notes, 1967-1973 (Box 9)
    - X614, Colloquium in Medieval Science, Spring 1982 (Box 9)
    - X616, Ancient Atomism, Fall 1968; (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - X617, Fall 1988 (Box 9)
    - X705, Seminar in History of Medieval Science (Box 9)
      - Spring 1996 (Box 9)
      - Lecture on Med. Natural Philosophy, Spring 1996 (Box 9)
      - Medieval universities, Spring 1996 (Box 9)
      - The Medieval university and the reception of Aristotelian learning, Spring 1996 (Box 9)
      - Translations, Spring 1996 (Box 9)
      - Doing science in late middle ages, Spring 1996 (Box 9)
      - Renaissance of late 12th Cent., Spring 1996 (Box 9)
    - Seminar: Medieval Optics, Spring 1963 (Box 9)
    - Course Proposal: Medieval World View, undated (Box 9)
    - Bibliographies: Medieval Science, undated (Box 9)
    - Ph.D. Qualifying Exams, 1969; 1980; 1991-1993 (Box 9)
    - El04 (Box 9)
      - Occult, Spring 2000 (Box 9)
      - Clippings, Spring 2000 (Box 9)
      - 10 week exam, Spring 2000 (Box 9)
      - 15 week exam, Spring 2000 (Box 9)
- Student work, 1950-1959
  - City College in New York (Box 10)
    - Undergrad term paper, May 1950 (Box 10)
    - Ancient Science, Fall 1950 (Box 10)
    - History II-Ancient Greece, 1950 (Box 10)
    - Ancient History, undated (Box 10)
  - (University of Wisconsin) (Box 10)
    - History of Pharmacy, Fall 1951 (Box 10)
    - European Social/Intell. History, undated (Box 10)
    - Ancient philosophy, Fall 1951 (Box 10)
    - History of Science 1a, Fall 1951 (Box 10)
    - 120b History of Science, Spring 1951-1952; (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - History of Science, Fall 1952 (Box 10)
    - Medieval philosophy, Spring 1952-1953 (Box 10)
    - Various grad courses, 1953; (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Notes, undated (Box 10)
    - Samuel Butler notes, undated (Box 10)
    - Term papers for hist. of science, 1953; (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Term paper: Robert Bacon, undated (Box 10)
    - Term Paper: Dante and Renaissance, 1953 (Box 10)
    - 1a History of Science, Fall 1953 (Box 10)
    - 282 Hist. of Science, Fall 1953; (3 folders) (Box 10)
    - 170 Hist. of science, Spring 1953 (Box 11)